Register of the Eric Hoffer papers
Hoover Institution Archives
- Correspondence, 1941-1983
  - The Ledger Syndicate, Inc. (John W. Higgins)
    - 1969 (Box-folder 34: 5)
    - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 34: 6)
  - Lefever, Ernest W., 1973 (Box-folder 34: 7)
  - Lehmann, Edgar and Dorothy, 1951-1952 (Box-folder 34: 8)
  - Lestrud, Vernon, 1970-1972 (Box-folder 34: 9)
  - Levy, Alice and Jack, 1969-1973 (Box-folder 34: 10)
  - Lewton, Michael, 1964 (Box-folder 34: 11)
  - Life (Jack Fincher), 1967 (Box-folder 34: 12)
  - Lin, T. Y., 1969 (Box-folder 34: 13)
  - Lipton, Samuel D., 1951 (Box-folder 34: 14)
  - Leob, William, 1969-1979 (Box-folder 34: 15)
  - Look (Dan Fowler, Mike Land, Leonard Rubin), 1954-1968 (Box-folder 35: 1)
  - Lorand, Eugene J., 1966 (Box-folder 35: 2)
  - Los Angeles Times (Jim Bellows, William J. Drummond, Charles O'Rear, Art Seidenbaum), 1967-1970 (Box-folder 35: 3)
  - Lund, Bill, undated (Box-folder 35: 4)
  - Lund, S. E. Torsten, 1962 (Box-folder 35: 5)
  - Lynn, Cheryll, 1964 (Box-folder 35: 6)
  - Mancuso, Joyce, 1965 (Box-folder 35: 7)
  - Margolius, Hans, 1967 (Box-folder 35: 8)
  - Marshall, Henry, undated (Box-folder 35: 9)
  - Maucy, Christoph D., 1962 (Box-folder 35: 10)
  - May, Sally, 1968 (Box-folder 35: 11)
  - McCown, Leslie, undated (Box-folder 35: 12)
  - McDonald, Margaret, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 35: 13)
  - McGraw Hill Book Co. (Walter Clemons, Dan Lacy), 1968 (Box-folder 35: 14)
  - McLure, Fred, 1968 (Box-folder 35: 15)
  - Meijer, Hélène J., 1953 (Box-folder 35: 16)
  - Menninger, W. Walter, 1969-1982 (Box-folder 35: 17)
  - Michigan Technological University (R. L. Smith), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 35: 18)
  - Miller, Marjorie and Dora, 1960-1964 (Box-folder 35: 19)
  - Milner, Sara and Cooper, 1952-1962 (Box-folder 35: 20)
  - Mintz, Edward N., 1962 (Box-folder 35: 21)
  - Moisieve, Jack, undated (Box-folder 35: 22)
  - Montagu, Ashley, 1978 (Box-folder 35: 23)
  - Moore, Patricia, 1967 (Box-folder 35: 24)
  - Morain, Lloyd, 1956-1962 (Box-folder 35: 25)
  - Mound, Helen, 1969 (Box-folder 35: 26)
  - Moynihan, Daniel P., 1970-1974 (Box-folder 35: 27)
  - Mudrick, Marvin, 1972-1977 (Box-folder 35: 28)
  - Muhlenberg College (John M. Morey), 1975 (Box-folder 35: 29)
  - Murphy, George, 1970 (Box-folder 35: 30)
  - Muskie, Edmund S., 1969 (Box-folder 35: 31)
  - National Advisory Council on Adult Education (Leonard R. Hill), 1971 (Box-folder 35: 32)
  - National Institute of Arts and Letters (Felicia Geffen, John Hersey, Hannah Josephson), 1964 (Box-folder 35: 33)
  - Neighbor, J. Bruce, 1968 (Box-folder 35: 34)
  - New America (Paul Feldman, Michael Harrington), 1971 (Box-folder 35: 35)
  - New Republic (Gilbert A. Harrison, Michael Straight), 1954-1966 (Box-folder 35: 36)
  - New York Times (Jack Beck, Lewis Bergman, Barbara Dubivsky, William C. FitzGibbon, Howard Goldberg, John Harvey, Lester Markel, Dirk F. Ruemenapp, Harrison Salisbury, David Schneiderman, Harvey Shapiro, J. G. Stewart, Gerald Walker, Mary Beth Weinstein, John M. Willig), 1953-1974 (Box-folder 36: 1)
  - New Yorker (William Shawn), 1967 (Box-folder 36: 2)
    See also: Tomkins, Calvin
  - Nielsen-Lange, J., 1952 (Box-folder 36: 3)
  - Nisbet, Robert and Caroline, 1972-1978 (Box-folder 36: 4)
  - Nixon, Richard M., 1968-1972 (Box-folder 36: 5)
  - Northwest Review (Robert L. Curry, Jr.), 1962 (Box-folder 36: 6)
  - Nugent, Luci Johnson, undated (Box-folder 36: 7)
  - O'Brien, Bob and Norma, 1951 (Box-folder 36: 8)
  - Occidental College (John S. McNally), 1967 (Box-folder 36: 9)
  - Ogg, Wilson Reid, 1963 (Box-folder 36: 10)
  - Okerlund, Ed and Janet, 1978 (Box-folder 36: 11)
  - Ollagend, Professor, undated (Box-folder 36: 12)
  - Oltmans, Willem, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 36: 13)
  - Osborne, Eric, undated (Box-folder 36: 14)
  - Osborne, Lili Fabilli, 1964-1980 (Box-folder 36: 15)
    For correspondence with persons other than Eric Hoffer, see LILI FABILLI OSBORNE FILE.
  - Osborne, Selden, 1964 (Box-folder 36: 16)
  - Osborne, Steve, 1965-1979 (Box-folder 36: 17)
  - Osborne, Tonia, undated (Box-folder 36: 18)
  - Ostrach, Herb, 1957-1958 (Box-folder 36: 19)
  - Pacheco, Roland, 1973-1974 (Box-folder 36: 20)
  - Parssinen, Jan, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 36: 21)
  - Peace Corps (Brent Ashabranner, Joseph Blatchford, Roderick French, G. Payne Lucas, Wavie M. McCarthy, Louis Mitchell, Jerry Norris, Jack Vaughn), 1967-1969 (Box-folder 36: 22)
  - P.E.N. (Charles Rolo), 1965 (Box-folder 36: 23)
  - Peterson, Everette and Sonya, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 36: 24)
  - Phelps, Orme W., undated (Box-folder 36: 25)
  - Phillips, Pauline (pseudonym, Abigail Van Buren), 1969-1971 (Box-folder 36: 26)
  - Playboy (Marilyn Grabowski, James Morgan, A. C. Spectorsky), 1967-1978 (Box-folder 36: 27)
  - Pope, George, 1965 (Box-folder 36: 28)
  - Post, Helen, 1967 (Box-folder 36: 29)
  - Powell, Donald F., 1970 (Box-folder 36: 30)
  - Prentice-Hall, Inc. (Hedy Bergida, Steve Chawkins, Walter L. Meagher), 1965-1971 (Box-folder 36: 31)
  - President's Commission on White House Fellows (Joan K. Benziger, Bruce H. Hasenkamp, Thomas W. Pauken, Stephen P. Strickland), 1968-1976 (Box-folder 36: 32)
  - Pryor, Brandt, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 36: 33)
  - Quea, Thomas C., 1973 (Box-folder 37: 1)
  - Quinlan, Wayne, 1966-1972 (Box-folder 37: 2)
  - Reader's Digest (Catherine Conklin, Charles W. Ferguson, Nora J. Hair, Willard F. Hamilton, Virginia Kelly, Peter Kristoph, Laura McCormick, Marjorie Nicholson, Henry Ohkawa), 1966-1982 (Box-folder 37: 3)
  - Reagan, Ronald, 1969 (Box-folder 37: 4)
  - Redbook (Robert J. Levin), 1967 (Box-folder 37: 5)
  - Reiff, Robert, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 37: 6)
  - Republican Party (Jeremiah Milbank, Jr.), 1972 (Box-folder 37: 7)
  - Rice, Dan, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 37: 8)
  - Robbins, Carolyn, 1981 (Box-folder 37: 9)
  - Roberts, Erling and Muriel, 1969-1970 (Box-folder 37: 10)
  - Roberts, Malcom and Cindy, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 37: 11)
  - Robinson, Michael, undated (Box-folder 37: 12)
  - Rockefeller, Nelson, 1968 (Box-folder 37: 13)
  - Rogers, Abe, 1971 (Box-folder 37: 14)
  - Rose, Leo, 1974-1978 (Box-folder 37: 15)
  - Ross, Nancy, undated (Box-folder 37: 16)
  - Roth, Lester, 1968 (Box-folder 37: 17)
  - Rowand, E. C., Jr., 1965-1980 (Box-folder 37: 18)
  - Rowley, Horace P., 1977 (Box-folder 37: 19)
  - Royce, Katharine, 1967-1968 (Box-folder 37: 20)
  - Rustin, Bayard, 1969 (Box-folder 37: 21)
  - San Francisco Examiner (Virginia Bullivant, Thomas Eastham, Charles L. Gould, Donald Grant, Lisa Hobbs, Steve McNamara, Luther Nichols, Robert Patterson, M. H. Shector, Guy Wright), 1959-1970 (Box-folder 37: 22)
  - San Francisco Public Library (David E. Belch, William R. Holman, Ruth M. Isaacs, William L. Ramirez), 1962-1968 (Box-folder 37: 23)
  - Sand, Morton, 1981 (Box-folder 38: 1)
  - Saturday Review (Sydney Bridgman, Norman Cousins, Jane M. Dozier, William H. Honan, Susan Stanwood, Horace Sutton, Ardeane Tratzki), 1962-1979 (Box-folder 38: 2)
  - Saxby, Sheila McDorney, 1971-1977 (Box-folder 38: 3)
  - Scalapino, Robert and Dee, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 38: 4)
  - Schuyler, George S., 1964-1965 (Box-folder 38: 5)
  - Schwartz, Robert L., 1962-1980 (Box-folder 38: 6)
  - Sciera, Leo, 1968 (Box-folder 38: 7)
  - Seabury, Paul, undated (Box-folder 38: 8)
  - Seeger, Pete, 1979 (Box-folder 38: 9)
  - Sevareid, Eric, 1967-1983 (Box-folder 38: 10)
  - Sexton, Brendon, 1952 (Box-folder 38: 11)
  - Shaplin, Helen, 1968 (Box-folder 38: 12)
  - Sherman, Barbara and Tex, 1977-1979 (Box-folder 38: 13)
  - Sherwood, Ann, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 38: 14)
  - Shipley, Norman, 1978 (Box-folder 38: 15)
  - Shockley, William, 1968-1973 (Box-folder 38: 16)
  - Shorenstein, Walter H., 1968-1978 (Box-folder 38: 17)
  - Showalter, Monica, 1980 (Box-folder 38: 18)
  - Simmons, Pat, 1965 (Box-folder 38: 19)
  - Singer, Max and Suzanne, 1968-1982 (Box-folder 38: 20)
  - Skeptic (Henry B. Burnett, Jr., Christiane Schlumberger), 1976 (Box-folder 38: 21)
  - Spector, Herman K., 1964 (Box-folder 38: 22)
  - Spees, Richard L., 1971 (Box-folder 38: 23)
  - Spelotti, Katia, 1964 (Box-folder 38: 24)
  - Sponberg, Gus, 1968 (Box-folder 38: 25)
  - Stafford, William E., 1963-1964 (Box-folder 38: 26)
  - Stanford University (Julius Duscha), 1967 (Box-folder 38: 27)
  - Steiner, Charles S., 1969-1977 (Box-folder 39: 1)
  - Stern, Alec, 1962-1968 (Box-folder 39: 2)
  - Stern, Erich, 1968 (Box-folder 39: 3)
  - Stokes, Robert C., 1965-1982 (Box-folder 39: 4)
  - Stone, Ezra, 1969 (Box-folder 39: 5)
  - Stone, Jim and Paula, 1971 (Box-folder 39: 6)
  - Stonehill College (John T. Corr, Paul L. McPherran), 1971 (Box-folder 39: 7)
  - Straub, Jeff, 1973-1982 (Box-folder 39: 8)
  - Straub, Pat and Robert, 1968-1978 (Box-folder 39: 9)
  - Stucky, William, 1958 (Box-folder 39: 10)
  - Sturtevant, John, 1978-1979 (Box-folder 39: 11)
  - Sulzbach, Ed, 1969 (Box-folder 39: 12)
  - Torczyner, Jacques, 1969 (Box-folder 40: 1)
  - Troxell, John, 1965-1980 (Box-folder 40: 2)
  - Tyrell, R. Emmett, Jr., 1972-1973 (Box-folder 40: 3)
  - United States. Air Force (Jack N. Donohew, George J. Eade, Victor J. Fraley, Frank O. Hinckley, George Kolt, L. S. Lightner, Wayne J. Lobbestael, Thomas S. Norman, S. J. Velarde), 1968-1973 (Box-folder 40: 4)
  - United States. Army (Jack L. Capps, W. C. Magathan, Joseph B. Messing), 1969-1974 (Box-folder 40: 5)
  - United States. Department of Health, Education, and Welfare (Elliot Richardson, James B. Roberts), 1970-1971 (Box-folder 40: 6)
  - United States. Department of Labor (Esther Peterson), 1968 (Box-folder 40: 7)
  - United States. Department of State (George V. Allen, Bernice W. Behrens, George M. Bennsky, Samuel D. Berger, J. Y. Bryan, Dixon Donnelley, Eloise R. Lee, Howard P. Mace, Elbert G. Mathews, Camilla McComber, Blanche T. Moore, John F. Root, Madeleine H. Russell, Peter S. Stern, Seymour Weiss), 1952-1975 (Box-folder 40: 8)
  - United States. Library of Congress (John C. Broderick, Nathan R. Einhorn), 1968-1972 (Box-folder 40: 9)
  - United States Civil Service Commission (Cradoc L. Bagshaw, Gerald R. Larion, John C. Matejka, John A. Rehfuss, Harry Wolf), 1967-1975 (Box-folder 40: 10)
  - United States Information Agency (Richard L. Borden, Nathan Glick, Ruth Hopkins, Frances G. Robinson, Alan E. Shevach, Garrett K. Sias, Stephen W. Wordell), 1962-1975 (Box-folder 40: 11)
  - University of California, Berkeley (Ruth Blumberg, Claire Boskin, James M. Boyd, Paul R. Chernoff, Ruth N. Donnelly, Roger W. Heyns, Thomas P. Jenkin, Robert F. Kerley, David T. McKibben, Martin Meyerson, Carl G. Rosberg, Jr., Sheila M. Saxby, Robert A. Scalapino, Aaron Wildavsky, Frederick M. Wirt, Jane Zahn), 1955-1975 (Box-folder 40: 12)
  - University of Southern California (John R. Hubbard, James A. Peterson), 1972-1973 (Box-folder 40: 13)
  - Van Geuns, Robert E., 1968-1981 (Box-folder 40: 14)
  - Van Zanten, Eda, 1951 (Box-folder 40: 15)
  - Vetter, George B., 1951-1958 (Box-folder 40: 16)
  - Vieg, John A., 1959-1969 (Box-folder 40: 17)
  - Viereck, Peter, 1951 (Box-folder 40: 18)
  - Vree, Dale, 1973-1979 (Box-folder 40: 19)
  - Wadleigh, Alice, 1968-1977 (Box-folder 41: 1)
  - Wadleigh, Frank, 1969-1977 (Box-folder 41: 2)
  - Wainwright, Don, undated (Box-folder 41: 3)
  - Ward, Marjorie, 1952 (Box-folder 41: 4)
  - Warwick, Robert H., 1952 (Box-folder 41: 5)
  - Wasserman, Louis, 1967-1969 (Box-folder 41: 6)
  - Wentz, Keith, 1967-1978 (Box-folder 41: 7)
  - Wessling, Herb, 1970-1982 (Box-folder 41: 8)
  - Westfahl, Wesley and Thelma, 1971 (Box-folder 41: 9)
  - Wexler, Jerome J., 1963-1972 (Box-folder 41: 10)
  - Whyte, Robert, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 41: 11)
  - Wiesenthal, Simon, 1969 (Box-folder 41: 12)
  - Wiggins, Anne, 1967-1980 (Box-folder 41: 13)
  - Wilmer, Harry, 1966-1978 (Box-folder 41: 14)
  - Wilner, Norman, 1966 (Box-folder 41: 15)
  - Wolf, Jeanne, 1977-1980 (Box-folder 41: 16)
  - Wolfe, Cameron W., Jr., 1974-1983 (Box-folder 41: 17)
  - Wood, Kenneth, 1970 (Box-folder 41: 18)
  - Woon, Basil, 1951 (Box-folder 41 :19)
  - Yates, Margaret and Randall
    - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 42: 1)
    - 1968-1973 (Box-folder 42: 2)
  - Young, Fred, 1974-1981 (Box-folder 42: 3)
  - Zaugg, Ernie, 1963-1979 (Box-folder 42: 4)
  - Zetzer, Henry J., 1966 (Box-folder 42: 5)
- Speeches and Writings, 1934-1983
  Articles, diaries, drafts of books, proofs, printed copies of books, speeches, television interviews, and anthologies, arranged chronologically by title, and translations, listed at the end.
  - "The Age We Live in,", undated (Box-folder 42: 6)
    Typescript
  - "Always and Today,", undated (Box-folder 42: 7)
    Holograph
  - Aphorisms, undated (Box-folder 42: 8)
    Holograph and typescript
  - "Architects and Nature: On the Primacy of Man," speech, undated (Box-folder 42: 9)
    See also: SOUND RECORDINGS/Sound cassettes for recording of this talk
  - "Are Revolutions Revolutionary?,", undated (Box-folder 43: 1)
  - Article on American politics, undated (Box-folder 43: 2)
    Holograph fragment
  - Article on American society, undated (Box-folder 43: 3)
  - Article on intellectuals and the Cold War, undated (Box-folder 43: 4)
  - Article on modernization, undated (Box-folder 43: 5)
  - Article on violence, undated (Box-folder 43: 6)
  - "At Home," poem, undated (Box-folder 43: 7)
  - "The Awakening of Stagnant Societies,", undated (Box-folder 43: 8)
  - "Beware the Intellectual,", undated (Box-folder 43: 9)
  - "Bible,", undated (Box-folder 43: 10)
  - "The Bull of Phalaris,", undated (Box-folder 43: 11)
  - "Chance and Mr. Kunze,", undated (Box-folder 43: 12)
  - "Concerning Individual Freedom,", undated (Box-folder 43: 13)
  - "A Disillusioned World,", undated (Box-folder 43: 14)
  - "Domestication,", undated (Box-folder 43: 15)
  - "The Effects of the Negro Revolution,", undated (Box-folder 43: 16)
  - "Encounter in Trypton,", undated
    - Holograph (Box-folder 43: 17)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 43: 18)
  - "The Eternal Workingman's Point of View,", undated (Box-folder 43: 19)
  - "The Flow of Human Energies,", undated (Box-folder 43: 20)
  - "For My Black Brothers: Build Yourself a City," poem, undated (Box-folder 43: 21)
  - "Four Years in Hank's Young Life,", undated
    - Holograph (Box-folder 43: 22)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 43: 23)
  - "Freedom and the Masses,", undated (Box-folder 44: 1)
  - "From Town to Town and Other Stories,", undated (Box-folder 44: 2)
  - "The Human Factor,", undated (Box-folder 44: 3)
  - "Imitation,", undated (Box-folder 44: 4)
  - Index of writing topics, undated (Box-folder 44: 5)
  - "Innovators,", undated (Box-folder 44: 6)
  - "Islam and Modernization,", undated (Box-folder 44: 7)
  - "Jehovah and the Occident,", undated (Box-folder 44: 8)
  - "Juveniles,", undated (Box-folder 44: 9)
  - "More Thoughts,", undated (Box-folder 44: 10)
  - "The Old,", undated (Box-folder 44: 11)
  - Poem on the subject of mortality, undated (Box-folder 44: 12)
  - "The Pride and the Greatness,", undated (Box-folder 44: 13)
    Proofs
  - "The Process of Change,", undated (Box-folder 44: 14)
  - "Quotations and Comments,", undated
    - Holograph (Box-folder 44: 15-17)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 45: 1-3)
  - "The Readiness to Die,", undated (Box-folder 45: 4)
  - "Reading the Old Testament for the First Time,", undated (Box-folder 45: 5)
  - "The Role of the Educated,", undated
    - Holograph (Box-folder 45: 6)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 45: 7)
  - "The Sheepherder's Sorrow,", undated (Box-folder 45: 8)
  - Sketches for stories, undated (Box-folder 45: 9)
  - "Some Thoughts on Freedom,", undated (Box-folder 45: 10)
  - Story, undated (Box-folder 45: 11)
  - "Thoughts,", undated
    - Holograph notes (Box-folder 45: 12)
    - Holograph fragment (Box-folder 46: 1)
    - Holograph drafts (Box-folder 46: 2-8)
    - Typescript fragment (Box-folder 46: 9)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 46: 10-11)
  - "Thoughts: New Collection,", undated (Box-folder 47: 1)
  - "Thoughts and Aphorisms,", undated (Box-folder 47: 2)
  - "Thoughts on the Present,", undated (Box-folder 47: 3)
  - "Tramps and Pioneers,", undated (Box-folder 47: 4)
  - "Turning Points,", undated (Box-folder 47: 5)
  - "Unfinished Man: Thoughts on the Human Condition,", undated
    - Holograph (Box-folder 47: 6)
    - Typescript (Box-folder 47: 7)
  - Untitled manuscript, undated (Box-folder 47: 8)
  - "The Weak Things of the World,", undated (Box-folder 47: 9)
  - "What We Do unto Others,", undated (Box-folder 47: 10)
  - "Winter in the Middle West," poem, undated (Box-folder 47: 11)
  - Story written in El Centro, California, 1934 (Box-folder 47: 12)
  - Autobiographical writing, 1934-1936 (Box-folder 47: 13)
  - The True Believer, 1951
    - Outline (Box-folder 48: 1)
    - Holograph fragments (Box-folder 48: 2-3)
    - Holograph drafts (Box-folder 48: 4-7)
    - Holograph revisions (Box-folder 49: 1)
    - Proofs (Box-folder 49: 2)
    - Printed copies (Box-folder 49: 3-4)
      See also: Boxes 75 and 76 for foreign editions
    - Editorial comments by Evan Thomas (Box-folder 49: 5)
    - Reviews, 1951-1966 (Box-folder 49: 6)
    - Anthologies containing excerpts from The True Believer
      - Robert A. Goldwin, Ralph Lerner, Gerald Strouzh, eds., Readings in World Politics, 1957 (Box-folder 49: 7)
      - Edgar Litt, eds., The Political Imagination, 1966 (Box-folder 50: 1)
      - Randall E. Decker, eds., Patterns of Exposition, 1969 (Box-folder 50: 2)
      - Leonard S. Silk and Phillip Saunders, eds., Readings in the World of Economics, 1969 (Box-folder 50: 3)
      - Robert A. Goldwin and Tony Pearce, eds., Readings in World Politics, second edition, 1970 (Box-folder 50: 4)
      - Frederick Gentles and Melvin Steinfield, eds., Dream On, America, 1971 (Box-folder 51: 1)
      - Gilbert Abacarian and Monte Palmer, eds., The Human Arena, 1971 (Box-folder 51: 2)
      - Harold E. King, Lorne N. Colter, John K. Dunn, Richard C. Hespen, John R. Staton, eds., The Mermaid's Head and the Dragon's Tail, 1972 (Box-folder 51: 3)
      - Claude E. Welch, Jr. and Mavis Bunker Taintor, eds., Revolution and Political Change, 1972 (Box-folder 51: 4)
      - E. Graham Ward, eds., Essays in Generalization, 1973 (Box-folder 51: 5)
      - Wilfred A. Ferrell and Nicholas A. Salerno, eds., Strategies in Prose, 1973 (Box-folder 52: 1)
      - William Gamson and Andre Modigliani, eds., Conception of Social Life, 1974 (Box-folder 52: 2)
  - "What Makes Nations Run Amuck?," This Week, 1951 December 2 (Box-folder 52: 3)
  - Unpublished aphorisms, 1952 July 26 (Box-folder 52: 4)
  - "The Nature of Stalinist Terror," This Week, 1952 August 17 (Box-folder 52: 5)
    Correspondence, typescript, and printed copy
  - "The Role of the Undesirables," Harper's, 1952 December
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 52: 6)
    - Reprint, Rudolf Flesch, ed., Best Articles 1953 (Box-folder 52: 7)
  - "Why Captive Peoples Revolt," New York Times Magazine, 1953 August 23
    - Typescript (Box-folder 53: 1)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 53: 2)
  - "The Workingman Looks at the Boss," Harper's, 1954 March (Box-folder 53: 3)
    Correspondence and printed copy
  - "The Process of Change," The Reporter, 1954 March 2 (Box-folder 53: 4)
  - "The Awakening of Asia," The Reporter, 1954 June 22 (Box-folder 53: 5)
  - "A Future for Intellectuals," The New Leader, 1954 August 16 (Box-folder 53: 6)
  - "The Passionate State of Mind," Harper's, 1954 December (Box-folder 53: 7)
  - "The Man of Words,", 1955 (?) (Box-folder 53: 8)
  - "Men of Words,", 1955 (?)
    - Notes (Box-folder 53: 9)
    - Holograph (Box-folder 53: 10)
  - The Passionate State of Mind, 1955
    - Holograph drafts (Box-folder 53: 11-12)
    - Typescript drafts (Box-folder 54: 1-3)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 54: 4)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 54: 5)
  - Untitled writing, 1955 (Box-folder 54: 6)
  - "The Intellectual and the Masses," The Pacific Spectator, Winter, 1956
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 54: 7)
    - Japanese translation published in Americana, 1956 October (Box-folder 54: 8)
      Printed copy and correspondence
    - Vietnamese translation published in Huong Xa, 1958 October (Box-folder 54: 9)
  - "God and the Machine Age," The Reporter, 1956 February 23 (Box-folder 55: 1)
  - "The Rise and Fall of the Practical Sense," The Reporter, 1958 December 11 (Box-folder 55: 2)
  - "Thoughts on the Brotherhood of Men," New York Times Magazine, 1959 February 15
    - Proofs (Box-folder 55: 3)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 55: 4)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 55: 5)
    - Reprint, Lester Markel, ed., Background and Foreground, 1960 (Box-folder 55: 6)
    - Reprint, Sara L. Chalghian and Timothy G. Davies, eds., What I Meant to Say Was…, 1966 (Box-folder 55: 7)
  - Lecture given at San Francisco State College, 1959 March 30 (Box-folder 55: 8)
    Class resolution and student papers
  - "How Natural Is Human Nature?," The Saturday Evening Post, 1962 January 13
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 55: 9)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 55: 10)
    - Reprint, American Journal, 1963 March (Box-folder 55: 11)
  - "Imitation and Fanaticism," Northwest Review, 1962 Spring (Box-folder 55: 12)
  - "What Has Happened to Our Morality?," collective article including a contribution from Hoffer, New York Times Magazine, 1962 June 10 (Box-folder 55: 13)
  - "Conversations with Eric Hoffer," television interview conducted by James Day, KQED Television, 1963
    - Holograph transcripts (incomplete) (Box-folder 56: 1)
    - Typescript transcripts, nos. 1-6 (Box-folder 56: 2)
  - The Ordeal of Change, 1963
    See also: Box 76 for foreign editions
    - Notes (Box-folder 56: 3)
    - Holograph fragments (Box-folder 56: 4)
    - Holograph drafts (Box-folder 56: 5-6)
    - Holograph drafts (Box-folder 57: 1-2)
    - Typescript drafts (Box-folder 57: 3-8)
    - Proofs (Box-folder 57: 9)
    - Proofs (Box-folder 58: 1)
    - Publisher's description and title pages (Box-folder 58: 2)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 58: 3)
    - Reviews (Box-folder 58: 4)
    - Anthologies containing excerpts from The Ordeal of Change
      - Sumner Ives and Stephen O. Mitchell, eds., Language, Style, Ideas, 1964 (Box-folder 58: 5)
      - Ned E. Hoopes, Who Am I?, 1969 (Box-folder 58: 6)
      - Harold M. Hodges, Jr., ed., Conflict and Consensus, 1973 (Box-folder 58: 7)
      - Voices of Concern, 1971 (Box-folder 59: 1)
      - Jack L. Nelson, Kenneth Carlson, Thomas E. Linton, eds., Radical Ideas and the Schools, 1972 (Box-folder 59: 2)
      - Robert C. Meredith, ed., An Anthology for Young Writers, 1975 (Box-folder 59: 3)
  - "The Writer in an Automated World," public discussion among Eric Hoffer, Robert Kirsch, and Kenneth Rexroth, California Library Association conference, San Francisco, 1963 December 11 (Box-folder 59: 4)
    Transcript published in California Librarian, 1964 April. Printed copy
  - "The Role of the Educated," speech, Wheeler Hall, University of California, Berkeley, 1964 (Box-folder 59: 5)
  - "The Negro Is Prejudiced against Himself," New York Times Magazine, 1964 November 29
    - Proofs (Box-folder 59: 6)
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 59: 7)
    - Correspondence, including published and unpublished letters to the editor (Box-folder 59: 8)
    - Reprint, U.S. News and World Report, 1964 December 28 (Box-folder 59: 9)
  - "How Natural Is Human Nature?,", 1964 December 21 (Box-folder 60: 1)
  - Speech on violence, Boalt Hall, University of California, Berkeley, 1965 April 2 (Box-folder 60: 2)
  - "A Time of Juveniles," Harper's, 1965 June (Box-folder 60: 3)
  - "Automation Is Here to Liberate Us," New York Times Magazine, 1965 October 24
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 60: 4)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 60: 5)
  - "A Strategy for the War with Nature," Saturday Review, 1966 February 5
    - Printed copy (Box-folder 60: 6)
    - Correspondence (Box-folder 60: 7)
  - "Making a Mass Elite," Holiday, 1966 March (Box-folder 60: 8)